<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of ministring at the communion-table when there is no Eucharist stated and discussed, upon occasion of a treatise entitled, Parish churches turn'd into conventicles, &amp;c. : together with some preliminary reflections made upon two papers in answer to that treatise.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21330</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12226498</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12226498</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56533</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25196)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56533)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 621:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of ministring at the communion-table when there is no Eucharist stated and discussed, upon occasion of a treatise entitled, Parish churches turn'd into conventicles, &amp;c. : together with some preliminary reflections made upon two papers in answer to that treatise.</title>
                  <author>T. A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ralph Holt, for Obadiah Blagrave ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to T.A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hart, Richard, --  Friend to all the conformable clergy and laity of the true and apostolical Church of England. --  Parish churches turn'd into conventicles.</term>
               <term>Public worship.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56533:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE CASE OF MINISTRING AT THE <hi>Communion-Table</hi> When there is no EUCHARIST.</p>
            <p>STATED And Diſcuſſed, upon occaſion of a Treatiſe Entitled, <hi>Pariſh Churches turn'd into Conventicles,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER With ſome Preliminary Reflections made upon two Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in Anſwer to that Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Ralph Holt,</hi> for <hi>Obadiah Blagrave,</hi> at the <hi>Bear</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> 1683.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56533:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:56533:2"/>
            <head>THE CASE OF MINISTRING AT THE <hi>Communion-Table</hi> When there is no EUCHARIST. STATED And Diſcuſſed, upon occaſion of a Treatiſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled, <hi>Pariſh Churches turn'd into Conventicles,</hi> &amp;c. In a Letter to <hi>I. B.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO your Second Letter received laſt <hi>Thurſday</hi> with the incloſed Diſſertation, I cannot but yield the Debt of an Anſwer ſomewhat ſooner, becauſe I perceive you expect it ſo fully; tho I could ſcarce at any time ſet about ſuch a Task as you ſet me, more incommodiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as being waſted with ſuch a Grievous Catarrh, Hoarſneſs, and Soreneſs, that as I was conſtrained on that <hi>Thurſday,</hi> to break off my
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56533:3"/> conſtant Attendance at Church this Lent, and keep cloſe within Doors; ſo next day to confine my ſelf to my Chamber, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure help for the following Lords day. But beginning through Gods goodneſs to be better at eaſe, I would not deferr to give you mine opinion of the Book. And that in the firſt place of the ſour Title; which I confeſs offended me, as I ſuppoſe it will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers lying under the ſame Guilt with me, which he makes very Notorious, and of that nature, whereby the nature of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is ſhaken, and her Reputation deeply wounded, not ſo deſervedly, nor juſtly, as is inſinuated or rather openly charged; as I ſuppoſe will in ſome meaſure appear in the Sequel of my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poliſhed Diſcourſe, and very haſty, as you may gather from the ſhort time and long Letter.</p>
            <p>But leſt it ſhould be imagined that I offend in the like ſharpneſs, or prejudice againſt the Author, I do here premiſe this ſincere profeſſion, That I do diſcern a great deal of Ingeniouſneſs, Acute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Nervouſneſs, and Weight in the Diſcourſe. And that being (as may be drawn from ſome Paſſages) given to the Study of the Law of this Nation, he ſhould ſhew ſuch an unuſual Zeal for the Power, and eſtabliſhed Orders of the Church, which I would to God, were with no leſs Conſcience obſerved by the Clergy it ſelf, this not excepted, which he contends for ſo vigorouſly. And that I flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not him, nor diſſemble with you, may be atteſted in part by your ſelf, who know I reſtored the Uſance of Miniſtration at the Communion-Table, or rather introduced it where it was not heard of in the Memory of Man: and ſo continued it for 7 years, when for cauſes, ſome not touched by him, and ſome endeavoured to be refuted by this Author, I deſiſted. I would not therefore be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on at any hand at preſent, as going about to confute what he delivers: but upon your requeſt, deliver mine own Thoughts ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what diverſe, not contrary to his, and that in theſe in Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I do fully Grant, and firmly believe, that it is moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the mind of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that the Office called the ſecond Service be performed at the Communion-Table; Circumſtances remaining the ſame, as when it was firſt ſo inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For ſeeing Circumſtances do vary the caſe egregiouſly, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Author of ſuch Orders is to be judged from the Motives, and Ends inducing to ſuch Conſtitutions; which ceaſing, or changing, the Intention of the Ordainers may be ſaid to ceaſe and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56533:3"/> change likewiſe: and conſequently, the Obligation to obſerve the firſt Inſtitutions according to the rigour of the Letter: Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or Inſtances whereof I ſhall afterwards give you.</p>
            <p>In the mean time I muſt here note how wide the Author of that reproachful Title to his Papers is [to wit, <hi>Pariſh Churches turned into Conventicles]</hi> from making the Omiſſion of Miniſtration at the Lords Table, Conventicling, or Phanatical. For, what (I beſeech Mr. <hi>H.)</hi> is Conventicling, or Phanaticiſm which I make Synonymous (however ſome that call themſelves the Sober Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters would fain deny this?) Doth it conſiſt in ſimple Omiſſion of ſome part of the Service abſolutely, and not rather in theſe two things principally, and in my opinion Eſſentially? Firſt to have a contrary judgement and affection againſt the Eſtabliſhed Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, and as far as ſafely and ſucceſsfully they may, ſtrennuouſly to oppoſe the ſame? And if a man be far from any of theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of mind and actions, yet neglects ſomewhat enjoyned (for that we may ſuppoſe at preſent, which we ſhall Queſtion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after) rather than oppoſes, is there no favour to be ſhown him, but he muſt be condemned for a Phanatick, and his Miniſtration for Conventicling? Or are the Pariſh Prieſts Phanatical, who obſerve not <hi>Holydays,</hi> and the Service of <hi>Wedneſdays</hi> and <hi>Frydays?</hi> Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they not (according to this Gentlemans Rule) worſe than Conventiclers; as I think before God they are, who come not to Church, nor go to Conventicles, but on Publick Days of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip profanely ſtay at home. Surely as perverſeneſs, and obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in errour, are by the Learned judged the formal part of an Heretick: So likewiſe is it of a Schiſmatick, or Schiſmatizer; the Material part being the errour it ſelf of no ſmall impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>And this is the ſecond Reaſon diſtinguiſhing Omſſion at moſt of a Circumſtance in Publick Worſhip from Conventicling: For ſee, and judge indifferently the whole worſhip of Conventiclers. Is it not in Matter and in Form both, and alſo in all Circumſtances as much different from the Church-worſhip, as they well can to bear up the Name of Chriſtian? Doth it not wholly proceed from their own humane Brain? An intolerable crime with them, when they whom they have made their Adverſaries cannot alledge direct and expreſs Scriptures for all they ſay, or do in Gods Worſhip? I am of St. <hi>Hilary</hi>'s mind of old, That not the love of Walls ſacred, alters the Worſhip, but the Doctrine and Worſhip rather changes,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56533:4"/> and unhalloweth the Place: And when the Imaginations of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men are graced with the Fabrick of a Lawful Church, the Church is diſgraced into a Meeting-Room, or Conventicling place. But where a Circumſtance, and that of Place is only changed, I am quite of another opinion, unleſs this be done out of Oppoſition. For what if we ſhould ſuppoſe a Miniſter ſhould be ſo abſurd as to change the time of the ſecond Service, and keep his due place of the Communion-Table, reading it after Dinner? This would be worſe than the former, but ſtill it would not be Conventicling, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs all Irregular Worſhip makes a Conventicle, which if ſo, it may make it Popery too, and with better Reaſon, ſuch as the Phanaticks never dreamt on, or dared never to utter. For Papiſts divide not their Service into ſeveral Places, but keep their Station where they began, uſing ſome variety of Geſticulations. But I have ſpoken more under this Head than I intended, and therefore break from hence to,</p>
            <p>The ſecond Propoſition intended, and that is, That it doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath given any direct Precept for reading that part of the Communion Service at the Lord's Table, which is to end without Actual Conſecration. This I am to make good by two Ways, Firſt by probable Circumſtances begetting this Perſuaſion, Secondly by Examining the Pregnancy and Validity ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the Reaſons to the contrary mentioned and urged by Mr. <hi>H.</hi> My firſt Part I ſhall endeavour to make good by fetching ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what farther my Conjectures. For I ſuppoſe 1. that the conſtant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our Church in following the Scripture as a true Rule of Doctrine and Worſhip, and that as interpreted by the moſt Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, Sound, and Holy Church of Chriſt met here with no Obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Exception; little or no cauſe being given her to ſwerve from her profeſſed Rule of Charity and Conformity. Now, as I have (if my memory fail me not) intimated unto you in Perſonal Diſcourſe, I do not find that any where in Ancient Churches, nor at this day out of <hi>England,</hi> in Reformed or Unreformed, in Eaſtern, or Weſtern Churches, that the Office of the Church was ſo divided, as that one part of it ſhould be ſaid in one Part, or Quarter of the Church; and another in another Part; but where it began, there it ended.</p>
            <p>It may ſeem therefore a more neceſſary than curious Inquiry, to learn whence our Church took up that Cuſtome ſo ſtrange every where elſe. For tho after greater Concourſes of Chriſtians, for their greater benefit drew down the Office of the Church from the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56533:4"/> Eaſtern Part, and Quire, into the Body of the Church, for better Diſtribution of the Service among the Multitude, yet ſtill, the Office deſigned for the day was entirely compleated in one Place. Neither can it be ſaid that our Desk-Service, or common daily Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is a diſtinct Service from that of the Communion Service, which ſome alledge, others making a threefold Service by vertue of the Litany added to the reſt, upon Special days, which I think can ſcarce be made good; yet if all this were true, (which I ſhall rather yield, than here diſpute) ſtill we ſhall want an ancient Precedent to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant this diviſion of our Service into ſundry Places.</p>
            <p>For as for that Ancient Diſtinction of the <hi>Miſſa,</hi> into that of the <hi>Fideles,</hi> and the <hi>Catechumeni,</hi> whereof that conſiſted in the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Supper and the Communicating therein; This was called <hi>Sicca,</hi> becauſe there were only certain Prayers preliminary and common to all, deſigned for Baptiſme, as well as Baptized, without Conſecration: and therefore was alſo ſometimes call'd <hi>Nautica,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it might be uſed at Sea, on Ship-board, where they judged it not ſafe to conſecrate, yet (as I was ſaying) in one and the ſame Place when joyntly uſed, they were performed. This Diſtinction mentioned coming neareſt to the Reſembling and Juſtification of our ſtop of the Communion Service, where there is no Conſecration, at the end of the Prayer for the Holy Catholick Church, is much aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted by <hi>Bartholomaeus Nervius</hi> in his defence of <hi>Caſſander,</hi> page 890, 891 of <hi>Caſſanders</hi> works. And is acknowledged by <hi>Chemnitius Exam. Trident. pag.</hi> 363. <hi>Part.</hi> And more largely by <hi>Caſſander</hi> himſelf out of <hi>Waldenſis, Socrates,</hi> and <hi>Durantus,</hi> in the 34 Ch. of his Liturgies. Which I chuſe to ſpeak of here, as well to juſtifie the like Practice in our Church, as alſo to ſhew, that ſuch Diſtinction in the Office can be no ſufficient ground to juſt ifie diſtinct Places of Worſhip: And therefore we are to fetch the cauſes from ſome other ground than this: And I am of opinion, that ſuch ſearch will be loſt Labour out of our own Church: And that in our own Church will be found a Singular <hi>Oeconomia,</hi> (as St. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> would call it) and Condeſcenſion to gain, in the Spring of our Reformation, by all means, ſome.</p>
            <p>For in truth I am not ſo well read in, or ſo well remember, the Antiquities of our Church, as to be able to ſay when the Desk or Reading Pew in the Body of the Church, came firſt to be appointed, tho I remember ſome no modern Articles of Biſhops Viſitations en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring after them, as appointed. But when ever they were firſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56533:5"/> appointed, I preſume to ſay; That they were intended not for Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers at all, but for Reading the Scriptures and Homilies to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Engliſh Tongue, which they had not the happineſs a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, at all to enjoy. But the whole Service of the Church was, as in Ancient Churches, all at the Altar, as they call it, the People then having not forgotten to gather together before the Prieſt, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves, as formerly in times of Popery: For they had not drunk in the Popular Superſtition of following Teachers, ſcaring them, as Children, with Bugbears of Superſtition in places. And when the ordinary daily Service was brought into the Desk, as moſt commodious, at the time of celebrating the Lords Supper, which was adjudged then requiſite to be continued, all <hi>Holydays,</hi> and <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days</hi> the Communion Service was continued as formerly, at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, as at firſt, or the Table, in the ſtead and place of the Altar. And I do really believe, but cannot demonſtrate, that until the firſt Book of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. enjoyned, all the Reformed Service was as formerly, at the Altar. But in that firſt Book I find no Rubrick directing the Service in the Body of the Church, or Chancel: But in the 2 Book of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. this Rubrick is premiſed. The Morning and Evening Prayer ſhall be uſed in ſuch places of the Church, Chappel or Chancel, and the Miniſter ſhall ſo turn him, as the People may beſt hear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is mention made of the moſt commodious Poſture at one Place for the People to hear: But no mention at all of divers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, either in the firſt Service, or in the ſecond, where is order taken more eſpecially for proper Habits at the time of celebration of the Communion, but nothing elſe, implying but one Place, as yet. Now when the Places become diſtinct by erecting a Reading Pew, I am of opinion, that it was then, and after permitted to Officiate then in the Second Service (as we call it) in the Desk, till the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of Conſecration, which the Ancients would call the Canon of the Maſs, began. For in ſuch Junctures, and Caſes, I believe it was the command of the Church there only to miniſter.</p>
            <p>And from hence I gather a Solution of the Riddle, and of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections made for the Direct Precept of our Church for Miniſtring the whole Office of the Communion at the Lords Table. The Difficulties and Arguments for the Indiſpenſable Obligation to it, are founded upon the certain Command, which I grant ought Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to be obeyed, that command certainly appearing. Command Direct none is pretended, but Indirect, and Implicite is endeavoured
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56533:5"/> to be proved by Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and others from a two-fold Rubrick, the one requiring that the Miniſter ſtand at the North end of the Table, which he cannot do, unleſs he be there. This is very true. But can he not be there, unleſs he be commanded to be there? Or may he not be commanded to be there, when he actually is to celebrate, and ſo have Rules appointed how to order his Actions, and Station through the whole, but this muſt oblige to that place when the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration doth not follow, nor is intended?</p>
            <p>Again, it is argued from a Rubrick ſaying, Then ſhall the Prieſt return to the Lords Table. And this ſay they neceſſarily implies that he was there before. I grant it. But the queſtion is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his being there upon ſome occaſions, and having been there upon ſuch occaſions (as namely preparing for a Communion before Sermon) he muſt return thither again having ended his Sermon. This teaches how he muſt demean himſelf when he is there, but does not prove that indiſpenſably he muſt be there at all times, when ſo much, and no more is ſaid, as reacheth to the proper Office of conſecration. That this is no Querk or groundleſs Evaſion, will competently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from the Rubrick immediately going before, which is this, Then ſhall follow the Sermon, or one of the <hi>Homilies</hi> already ſet forth by Authoirty. Let them tell me now, whether this be not a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Precept of our Church. Let them likewiſe tell, whether this be an abſolute command, or Conditional only. That is, whether the Miniſter having proceeded ſo far in that Service, is abſolutely bound to Preach, or read an Homily (which I know none will po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively affirm) or only obliged when there is a Sermon or Homily, here to have it. Which I doubt not but will generally be granted to be the very truth.</p>
            <p>From hence then in proportionable manner I inferr, that return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Lords Table is neceſſarily impoſed upon the Miniſter, when his Miniſtration required that he ſhould be there, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally, not when it did not require him. And if it be yet urged, that he is always required, this is to beg the queſtion, which could not be gained by Argument: And to fall into this circle he muſt needs be there becauſe he muſt return thither, and he muſt return thither becauſe he was there. And thus have I done with my firſt proof of my Propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> That the primary intention of our Church was (imitating ancient Churches) that the entire Service ſhould be ſaid in one place, and conſequently that ſhe never intended one part of the Communion Service ſhould be Executed in the Desk, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56533:6"/> at the Lords Table, but that remitting of its principal deſign in ſuffering the firſt Service, as now it is called, to be in the Desk, it is Probable that ſhe yielded, that ſo much of the ſecond might be there uſed, as related not neceſſarily to Conſecration. And ſo of the two main Reaſons arguing a neceſſity of the <hi>Miſſa Sicca</hi> to be out of the Desk.</p>
            <p>A Second Reaſon I make to be from not the Caſual, but the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Uncertainty of the Forementioned Rubricks diverſly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by divers Men. That there is no ſuch Convincing clearneſs in them, as is pretended, I ſhew from a paſſage I learned from one of Arch-Biſhop <hi>Juxons</hi>'s Chaplains upon the ſight of the laſt Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of our Liturgie under this King: Who obſerving the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks to Stand in that doubtful manner, as before, in the New Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where no Precept is given to miniſter out of the Time of the Lords Supper, and yet order taken how he that miniſters ſhall ſtand and return, was much offended with the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sheldon</hi> for not taking care of Rendring things more plain: but which way he deſired more Perſpicuity, I cannot tell, that this, whether by determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for conſtant Miniſtration at the Communion-Table, even where, and when no Communion was, I cannot ſay, or whether not.</p>
            <p>A Third Reaſon I take from the Apparent, and Indubitable Tenet of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is, That all Sacred and Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God be Intelligibly performed before the Common People, and more eſpecially the Scriptures then Rehearſed. This I could ſhew, if need Required, from the judgment of ſome of our Graveſt, and Learned'ſt Divines delivered to me upon this occaſion, Inſtanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them in this Inconvenience of the People not being able to hear, and much leſs to underſtand that which a man of Competent Voice Saith at the Altar, keeping their Seats in the Church, which hath more than one Alley, or Ile. You know mine hath three Alleys, and when I conſtantly uſed Miniſtration in the Chancel (which you know is none of the leaſt) I have been aſſured by ſome moſt affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Church-Service, that they could hear nothing of what I ſaid in the Chancel: And yet I am confident there are more Voices weaker, and lower than mine was, than lowder. Now what Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy can be made for ſuch unknown Tongue to them that hear it not, which may not be made for a Tongue abſolutely unknown, which is heard? I know none. I know in the <hi>Greek</hi> Liturgies of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten occur in their Rubricks <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> Lowly and Lowdly: But their Low Voice is there only appointed when they ſpeak not to the People, but apply themſelves directly and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56533:6"/> to God, as in actual Conſecration. And the Author of the <hi>Compilatio Chronologica,</hi> at the Year 484. amongſt the <hi>German Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> hath theſe words, <hi>Tres Cauſae ob quas ſub ſilentio pronunciat Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Miſſae:</hi> 1 <hi>Quia Deo loquitur.</hi> 2 <hi>Taedium crearet Populo &amp; Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doti.</hi> 3. <hi>Ne vileſcant Verba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like cauſes may you find in <hi>Biel Lect.</hi> 15. or the <hi>Maſs</hi> and yet more fully in <hi>Vicecomes Vol.</hi> 3. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 23. which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Church of <hi>England</hi> never purpoſely hideth from the People any part of the Service, tho by accident all may not be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of what is ſaid openly: But looks upon it as a Corruption befalling the Worſhip of God in Tract of time: Ancienter Days allowing Explicite and Audible Pronunciation of thoſe things which after-Ages made too Myſtical to be made Common: As you may find well Proved by <hi>Spalatenſis Reipub. Eccleſiaſt. Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Ch.</hi> 6. <hi>Num.</hi> 11. And <hi>Photius Nomocanon. Tit.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. proves the ſame out of the 5 Canon of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> and 5 <hi>Baſil,</hi> and the <hi>Code.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore much more doth our Church require ſuch Audible Miniſtrations. Which if ſhe does, how ſhe can require ſuch a Miniſtration, as ſhould neither be underſtood, nor ſo much as heard, Judge you.</p>
            <p>Two things I am very Senſible may be here Retorted, one whereof is mentioned by Mr. <hi>H.</hi> Firſt, That it may ſo fall out that a Man cannot be heard in the Desk, and ſo another manner of care ought to be taken againſt this Inconvenience as well as that. I anſwer, This is Poſſible, and doth divers times happen: But when the Church hath taken all Ordinary care to prevent an Inconvenience, and yet cannot, there is no more to be Expected from her, but ſuch rare Inconveniences muſt be ſuffered, to prevent Multiplicity of Remedies, which like the Frequentation of Phyſick to obviate eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little Indiſpoſition in the Body Natural, would prove worſe than the Diſeaſe. For as <hi>Plato</hi> was wont to ſay, To multiply Laws upon every light occaſion ſeeming uſeful, is to cut off <hi>Hydra</hi>'s Head, in place of which many will ſuddainly Spring up. Which by the way were to be wiſhed would be duly conſidered by our States-men, who preſently finding the Subject in the leaſt Incommoded, muſt make a Law to cut off that Grievance, not foreſeeing greater Evils ready to break out upon that Law. But to return, The Caſe is much different in the Service at the Lords Table, and in the Desk, when as the firſt by many is never heard, and the Second ſometimes not heard by ſome few.</p>
            <p>Another Objection may be, That as for the better hearing the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56533:7"/> Part of the Com. Service was brought into the Desk, ſo by the like Reaſon ought the other Conſecrating Part be there alſo fixed. To which my reply is that, Firſt, this by the Rubrick of that Office was, and is left to the Diſcretion of the Ordinary, who hath Power to bring the Com. Table into the Church, I ſuppoſe, when he Sees the Chancel uncapable of ſo great a Company as is to Communicate Ordinarly. Next I Anſwer, That there is a great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parity in the Caſes. For when People actually Communicate, they are not only Permitted, but invited to leave their Remoter Places, and Humbly to Preſent themſelves in the Chancel at a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent diſtance, ſo that they may heighten their Meditation by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, and Inflame their Devotions more fully, by hearing the Liturgiſt Officiate: But in the firſt Part this is not Permitted, nor would be liked.</p>
            <p>Will you Pleaſe to hear the Judgment of <hi>Martyn Bucer</hi> in his firſt Chapter of his Cenſure of the Engliſh Service concerning this Point? It is very Harſh, for one that was much more Gentle then his Fellow Reformers of that time: His Words are theſe, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t enim chorus ſit tam procul ſejunctus a reliquo Templo, &amp; in eo tantum Sacra repreſententur, quae tamen ad omnem pertinent Populum, Clerumque hoc Antichriſtianum eſt.</hi> I Engliſh nothing to you: For you know this to be ſevere. And little leſs is that of <hi>Merick Cauſabon</hi> Son of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and Late Prebend of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in his Treatiſe of Preaching <hi>Pag.</hi> 21. If I miſtake not, Speaking thus, However this Occaſion being giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me, I cannot but profeſs my Great Diſlike, that the Service, and Sermon ſhould be Parted any where, the one, in one Place, and the other in another, if it may poſſibly be avoided. Eſpecially at ſuch a diſtance, as it is here with us in the Cathedral, and Metropoliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Church of Chriſt in <hi>Canterbury.</hi> I Conceive it one Reaſon, that ſo few are acquainted, and by Conſequent, not more in Love with the Service. I leave this to Conſideration.</p>
            <p>But I gather from St. <hi>Aug.</hi> words in his firſt Book <hi>Contra Epiſtolam Permeniani,</hi> Ch. 7. That tho the Prieſt miniſter'd in the Chancel, yet the People both heard and underſtood, and ſaid <hi>Amen</hi> to the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as theſe words Teſtifie, <hi>Populus autem, cujus ille Sacerdos eſt, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc foris gemit: Nam cum Epiſcopus ſolus intus eſt, Populus &amp; orat cum illo, &amp; quaſi ſubſcribens ad ejus Verba, Reſpondet</hi> Amen. This <hi>being within</hi> of the Biſhop, and this <hi>foris,</hi> or without, of the People, who anſwered <hi>Amen</hi> to his Prayers, was much different from our Church and Chancel. For indeed they ſeem to be divided not much
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56533:7"/> otherwiſe than that Place within the Rails from the reſt of the Chancel; or as myſelf have ſeen in ſome <hi>Greek</hi> Churches, as a Skreen with two Doors divides one Part of an Hall from another, which hindered not the People from partaking of what was there with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in done by the Biſhop or Prieſt. But when Zeal toward the moſt Sacred Place, (as they judged that, wherein the Service of God was ſpecially performed) cauſed men to build Ample Chancels diſtinct from the Body of the Church (to Speak the Plain truth) they fell into a Pious Errour, and brought great Inconvenience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Publick Service of God in the Judgment of all thoſe, who look upon unknown, or unheard of Worſhip; as contrary to true Chriſtian Communion. Of the Number of which ſeeing our Church hath ever Profeſſed it ſelf, how can we fairly ſuppoſe ſhe ſhould contradict her own Doctrine by her Practice. And thus far of my Second Propoſition.</p>
            <p>My third and laſt Propoſition (for 'tis more than time that this Diſcourſe were ended) is this. That upon Suppoſition that once it was the real Intention of our Church, that no Part of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Service, even when there was no Communion, ſhould be ſaid any where but at the Communion-Table, Cuſtom hath both weakned that Law, and Interpreted the meaning of the Church ſo far otherwiſe, that it cannot deſerve that odious Name of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticling to Read one Part of it in the Desk. This I purpoſely ſet down thus, and directly oppoſe to the main Column of this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Diſcourſe built on the contrary, which he farther Buttreſſeth, (as I may ſo Speak) with many Inferior Reaſons: As the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs of Cuſtom to overthrow a Law. For tho ſaith he well, <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. a Cuſtom not prevented by a Law, maketh a Law, yet where a Law goeth before inconſiſtent with the Cuſtom, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom cannot, and ought not to Null that Law, being not orderly Reſcinded.</p>
            <p>Again, (I give his meaning, not ſticking to his words) it is a Grievous Affront to the Kings Majeſty, and Authority, thus by Cuſtom to be Baffled. It is a Great Breach upon the Churches Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to have her Canons and Orders thus ſlighted. It is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable Preſumption for Private Prieſts of their own Heads without good Authority, to judge of what is Convenient or Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, what is Decent, or Indecent, what Superſtitious, or not Superſtitious, contrary to Publick Decrees, and I may add, it is the Peſt, and Ruin of this, and all other Eſtabliſhed Churches, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56533:8"/> Charitable Complyance, with pretended tender Conſciences of Private Men againſt the Conſcience, and maturer Counſels of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours. All this I acknowledge to be very important, and deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing due Conſideration: Which I ſhall endeavour to give to it, by opening briefly the Power, and Nature of Cuſtom, not only when there is no Written Law to the contrary, but where there is. And this I ſhall do by running through, and giving Inſtances in all ſorts of Laws, as Civil, Common Law with us; Canon Law with other Churches as well as ours, in all which it will appear what Great Influence and Efficacy Cuſtom hath over them; and ſo, no ſuch new, notorious, or Intolerable thing is ſaid or committed in Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom here predominating over the General Rule here ſuppoſed by that worthy Gentleman.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with the Judgment of that Learned Dr. <hi>Eaden,</hi> late Maſter of Trinity-Hall in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Inferiour to few of his Time, and none of this Nation in knowledge of the Civil Law, as I am aſſured by thoſe that knew him better than I did. It being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him, what he thought of Cuſtom contrary to an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed Law, or Statute of a Colledge ſpecially? He anſwered, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom doth prevail in ſuch Caſes. And being urged a Second time, and demanded, But what if there be ſuch a Law made that ſaith, by way of Anticipation of abuſe of Cuſtom, that no Cuſtom which afterward may poſſibly ariſe ſhall make void ſuch a Law, ſhall Cuſtom prevail alſo againſt ſuch a Law? Yes, (anſwered he) Cuſtom is to be obſerved againſt ſuch a Law alſo.</p>
            <p>And that he ſpake not without Book (as they ſay) or without good Reaſon, I ſhall ſhew, beginning with the Civil Law. But firſt of all muſt we agree what Cuſtom is. <hi>Conſuetudo,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iſidore Hiſpalenſis, Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>C.</hi> 3.) <hi>eſt jus moribus inſtitutum.</hi> Now it is not ſo well agreed upon by the Learned <hi>Civillians</hi> what Continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Practice maketh a Lawful Cuſtom. Some Lawyers, and Laws, (as I could Inſtance in, were it ſeaſonable) make twenty Years a Competent time to produce, and denominate a Cuſtom; others Aſſign an Hundred Years, others forty. Now chooſe which we will of theſe three, there will be good Ground to found a Cuſtom of not neceſſary Obſervation of the Service at the Communion Table, out of Communion. For tho (as Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> ſaid, <hi>quoted</hi> by Mr. <hi>H.)</hi> the ſaid Service was commonly there uſed, when there was no Communion; yet it is much more certain that more Common and General it was to omit it, and that for theſe Hundred Years.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56533:8"/> And beſides Experience, I think the Argument of the quarrelſome Sectaries, do prove ſo much, who would not have dared (tho they be daring enough) to have called it an Innovation, had it been in the Memory of Man Generally obſerved.</p>
            <p>But in truth, it was their wonted, and affected Ignorance, which ſo Venturouſly and Miſchievouſly tranſports them oftentimes to call it an Innovation, when they could not be ſo ſtupid many of them that had ever ſeen and been preſent at a Cathedral, but they muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it to be almoſt as Ancient as the Reformation, than which they are wont to deſire nothing Ancienter. Here therefore we may bring in the finer Diſcourſes of ſuch who will diſtinguiſh Uſe from Cuſtom. For Uſe may that be called, that which is not altogether laid aſide: But Cuſtom that which is moſt Common and Prevalent: And ſuch undoubtedly is this Omiſſion we ſpeak of. Some add a third kind, which they call Preſcription, but <hi>Vaſquez</hi> in 1. 2. <hi>Thomae,</hi> tells them well, they are miſtaken: For as much as Preſcription differs from Cuſtom as to Degrees, or as a Child from a Man. One or two Acts or Examples the Lawyers will allow for a Sufficient Preſcription: but they cannot alledge them to be a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom: Cuſtom being that which for Multitude, and Extent exceeds all other Rules.</p>
            <p>Now for the force of Cuſtom, becauſe ſome are of opinion it dependeth upon Authority to be of Weight, I ſhall give you <hi>Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quez</hi> his Judgment in <hi>Thom.</hi> 1, 2, <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Diſput.</hi> 177. <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. § 52. <hi>Ego quidem,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Exiſtimo, ſi loquamur ſecundum jus Canonicum &amp; Civile Imperatorum, Conſuetudinem poſſe introduci abſque ullo actu Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciali, ſolo Extrajudiciali uſu. Nam in jure Canonico nullus textus eſt, in quo contrarium ſtatuatur; In Civili verò Imperatorio eſt lex quae exigat duas Sententias:</hi> That is, as I underſtand him, which required two Judgments, one taken from the Law written, another from the Law unwritten, or Cuſtom. And he that ſhall adviſe with <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 79. <hi>a.</hi> 3. and his Retinue of <hi>Commentators</hi> ſhall find theſe three Properties Generally aſcribed to Cuſtom. 1. That it abrogates and takes away the Law, which I confeſs I aſſent not to, giving my Reaſons hereafter, becauſe it only voids the Preſent Obligation to it, and not deſtroys it abſolutely. 2. It Interprets Law. This I hold generally true. 3. It brings in a New Law, <hi>i. e.</hi> there being no Law Antecedent oppoſing ſuch a Law: For in ſuch Caſes it only lays the Ancient Law aſleep, not kills it.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56533:9"/>
            <p> I might enlarge more upon this Preparatory Diſcourſe to Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom: But I come to the thing it ſelf, and the effects of it. Firſt in Civil Law, to make void (as even now I ſaid) the Letter of a Law Preſcribing otherwiſe: So that if beſides General Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Obedience to Lawful Governours, men for the firmer Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of it, and Obſervation, ſhall take an Oath to keep it, his Oath according to great Interpreters, doth not neceſſarily, and fully bind according to the Literal ſenſe, when a General and long Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom prevaileth to the contrary. I here to prove this, alledge the words of <hi>Gerſon</hi> Chancellour once of <hi>Paris, Coroll.</hi> 13. <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. <hi>De vitâ Spirituali;</hi> and the rather, becauſe Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath plainly ſaid, that ſuch <hi>Conſuetudo</hi> is no other than <hi>Corruptela,</hi> which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly confronted by theſe words of Grave <hi>Gerſon. Omnis Lex humana eſt vel Poſitiva, in eo quòd non neceſſario participat cum Naturali, &amp; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina. Haec autem Abrogatio fit vel per Conſuetudinem oppoſitam juxta quod dicunt Juriſtae, &amp; verum eſt, quod Conſuetudo est optima Legum In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpres. Nec unquam dicenda eſt Corruptela, niſi ubi Legem Divinam aut Naturalem laedere convincitur.</hi> And by and by he adds. <hi>Fit autem Abrogatio per Expreſſam, aut Interpretativam Revocationem fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ab illo, qui condendi habuit Poteſtatem: fit denique Abrogatio Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa manifeſtae Damnationis, ſi Lex illa Servetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is matter offered of a Refutation of Mr. <hi>Harts</hi> Suppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſuch a Cuſtom, as we now contend for, would be both a great Corruption, and Abrogation of the Law ſuppoſed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn this Practice. For this would be only an Interpretation of the mind of the Legiſlatour in the like Juncture of Weighty Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. Again, it would not be ſuch affront to the Kings and Churches Authority, they both looking on and permitting this Cuſtom enervating their Law. And beſides, where a Law is Abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated properly, there goeth before ſuch a Reciſion, and Repeal, which deny Power Ordinary to the Authors of that Law, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, that it no more can be of force without a New Act E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing it: but where long Cuſtom hath voided it for a time, it remains ſtill with the Diſpenſers of the Laws, whether Civil, or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, to Revive and Reinforce it, without any new Solemn, and formal Enacting of a new one.</p>
            <p>This farther appeareth from Statutes of Univerſities, Colledges in Univerſities, and Collegiate Churches: The Members of which oblige themſelves to a due Obſervation of them, and you ſee what great Latitude is ſuffered by vertue of Cuſtom ſubtilly, and Inſenſibly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56533:9"/> creeping upon ſuch Foundations, whereby as the Ivy eats out the Heart and Life of the Timber-Tree in time, the force of them is almoſt loſt. Of this the ſame <hi>Gerſon</hi> in the ſame Place <hi>Lectur.</hi> 4. thus taketh notice, <hi>Nobis praeterea dicendum videtur multae ſunt Inſtitutiones, ad quarum Obſervationes videntur Omnes ſe Quotidianis Juramentis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringere, quas tamen obſervare non tenentur. Non quod Perjurium ſit licitum, ſed quod talia Juramenta ſemper ſunt intelligenda civiliter. Horum Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empla ſumere poſſumus in praeclara <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitate Pariſienſi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what he means by Civil ſenſe of Precepts of our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours and Obedience of Inferiours, he intimateth to us in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe <hi>De Perfectione Cordis;</hi> that Obedience Sworn to our Rulers, extends not ſimply to all things, but only ſuch as their Power ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth unto; And in the former Treatiſe again our Obedience he makes fourfold. 1. Of Neceſſity 2. Of Congruity. 3. of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. 4. Of Perfection. So that in things not of Neceſſity, a low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Obligation tyeth us. <hi>Bernard. de Praecept. et Diſpenſ. c.</hi> 16. wiſely conſiders two things in taking upon a Man Obligation to Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, the <hi>Praeceptum</hi> againſt Sin, and the Remedy Provided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Tranſgreſſion of our Superiours Laws, and concludeth, <hi>Solum igitur exiſtimem fregiſſe votum, violaſſe propoſitum, praevaricaſſe pactum, qui &amp; praeceptum contempſerit &amp; remedium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we have the true and genuine Character of a Phanatick: For to violate a Law, ſo as to contemn it, and the Propounder of it, is to fall into Notorious Diſobedience, and Contumacie odious to God, and deſtructive to all Government: And having ſo done, to refuſe the Remedy of Admonition, and Submiſſion, is to be Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in modern Impiety: From which no Prieſt being Cenſured for not Miniſtring at the Altar according as our Author requires, and ſtill obſtinately refuſing, preferring his own ſenſe, and the will and good liking of the Common Sort, before Governours, can well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe himſelf: But while the Caſe is left at large, and notice taken of ſuch Omiſſion without Cenſure, the Caſe is altered.</p>
            <p>And I will now make this farther good from the Common-Law, from which Cuſtom hath given ſufficient Diſpenſation, the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in it's Native force unrepealed, and unabrogated: For which I ſhall follow the Judgement of that Learned Judge, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour <hi>Elſmere,</hi> in his famous Caſe of the <hi>Poſtnati, Page</hi> 48, 49, 50. Where he giveth divers Inſtances of change of Laws, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Determinations of Judges to Ancient Precedents and Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſtanding there unrepealed. Formerly, ſaith he, and ſhews
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56533:10"/> one Preſent, Aiding, Comforting, and Aſſiſting a Murther was tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to be no Principal, but an Acceſſory; but now is judged Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal. Again, the Remainder in Tall anciently could not have an Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Waſt againſt a Tenant for Life: But afterwards he might. Anciently the Vicar could not have an Action againſt the Parſon: But now he may, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And how came this Change but by Cuſtom? And how came this Cuſtom, but by one or two at firſt varying from the Ancient Rule? And yet the Kings Authority was not ſuppoſed hereby to be invaded or affronted, by which Ancient Laws Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted; which Mr. <hi>H.</hi> with great Zeal pretends muſt hereby won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully ſuffer, if ſo be ſuch a Change ſhould be made in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Laws.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon why the King and Church loſe nothing hereby, is, becauſe as Judges are Delegates of the King in Civil Matters, and being Subordinate to him, what they do paſſes as done by himſelf, he not entring his diſſent: So the Biſhops, ſo far as concerns the Civil Sanction of Laws Eccleſiaſtical, are deputed by the King to preſerve, and execute ſuch Laws, which if they do not, but by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hivence give way to a contrary Cuſtom, in time proving a Law, they are, if not Authors of, acceſſory to their own affronts, and ſwervers from the old Letter, thus by Practice interpreted, and in great Meaſure juſtified. A more apparent Inſtance of Yeſterday (as I may ſay) may be given in Cuſtom oppoſing and nulling the firſt Act of Parliament for Burying in Woollen, until it was Reinforced by a more Strict and Penal one. And another more Pregnant Inſtance we have in the Act requiring that all Waggons, and Travailing Carts ſhould have Broad Wheels, which never took Place, but being Generally neglected, that Act loſt it's end, and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour without repeal.</p>
            <p>And now, to touch upon the Canon-Law, and it's Obligations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt inveterate Cuſtom, I ſhall ſet down what I find in <hi>Biell, Lection</hi> the 3 on the Canon of the Maſs, out of <hi>Gerſon de Contract. Propoſit.</hi> 16. For I Remember not the Paſſage my ſelf in <hi>Gerſon,</hi> and am in too great haſt at preſent to ſearch for it. It is this. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Papa, vel Eccleſia, vel Legiſlator ſit, vel quando Conſtitutiones non pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licantur, ſed dantur oblivioni, vel non approbantur moribus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tentium</hi> (Note well this) <hi>ſed paſſim declinant in oppoſitum, tum Conſtitutiones illae deſinunt habere vim Obligationis, tanquam abolitae per non <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſum, vel Conſuetudinem oppoſitam, quae eſt optima Poſitivarum Legum Interpres.</hi> And it is well known to indifferently Learned in the Doctrine of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56533:10"/> Councils, and their Decrees, that there is a ſtrong Party in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, tho not the greateſt, that ſay, Acts of General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels oblige not until they be received: Yea, that a Council is then General, when it is received, and not otherwiſe, which tho it makes for my preſent purpoſe, is denied by me, as very abſurd to affirm.</p>
            <p>Yet this is moſt certain, (and I hope no man of Common inſight into Eccleſiaſtical Story will deny ſo far as to put any Body to the expence of ſo much Labour as to prove) that Innumerable Canons, and ſome called Apoſtolical, are totally laid aſide by a contrary Cuſtom growing upon them, and oppreſſing them. Let us only reflect upon things done at home, and concerning the keeping of <hi>Lent</hi> (the time I now write this) is there any more expreſs Law, or Canon for other things, than for this? And yet do not you ſee what a Groſs neglect there is in Obſerving it? And how few make a Conſcience, as they ought, of it? Doth not the Law ſtand as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and vallid, as ever, and yet Cuſtom prevaileth to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary? Are all Phanaticks that omit it? For my Part, if this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman ſhall ſay ſo, I will not oppoſe him, eſpecially if Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and Contumacy be found in the Caſe, or Piſhing, and Puſhing at the Authority of the Church, which alone ſuffices to Characterize a Sectary.</p>
            <p>And the like have I already ſaid, and ſhall ſay once more, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning not Officiating at the Lords Table accompanied with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and Contumacy, that it is Schiſmatical, and Phanatical. But I deny all Serving of God in Publick not exactly agreeing with the Liturgy, to be Conventicling, which this Gentleman affirms <hi>Pag.</hi> 7. but cannot prove. But then he demands <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. When a Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and what doing; how much, or how little differing he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Nonconformiſt? Certainly <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> being taken ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Etymology of the word, the leaſt difference in Practice makes a Nonconformiſt. But Nonconformiſt is of a more large and Civil ſenſe, rather than Grammatical in Common uſe. For the two Parts that make an Heretick, conſtitute a Schiſmatick too, and Nonconformiſt. Not every light Errour, but one of Moment, and not every one of Moment, but ſuch as is ſtoutly, and boldly defended makes an Heretick, and Nonconformiſt in Ceremonials.</p>
            <p>It is farther objected, That to approve the Multitudes forwardneſs, and Pretence of tender Conſciences againſt Authority, is to endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the whole State of the Church. I grant it to be moſt true, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56533:11"/> nothing can be more Pernicious to Eccleſiaſtical Order, Unity, or Charity, than Charity pretended to Private and Ignorant men's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences againſt the wiſer, and Weightier Determinations of our Governours: Eſpecially we conſidering Firſt, that no Juſt Cauſe is given for to offend Conſcience; and Secondly, that we muſt take their own bare word, that their Conſciences are really offended as is pretended, and that not rather ſome other wicked Paſſions, and Peeviſh, Envious, Ambitious Humour to be valued, and give Laws to their betters, wearing the Clothes of Conſcience, puts them upon ſuch Perverſe Diſputings, and Refractorineſs.</p>
            <p>To prevent which, it ſeems to concern Governours to judge fully of the End and Uſe, as well as Form of Laws, and eſpecially of the Form it ſelf, and accordingly to interpret, and enjoyn what doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be Legal, and Canonical, without ſuffering Cuſtom inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, but in Tract of time ſo ſtrongly to encroach upon them, that both their Authority, and the things Commanded ſhould become doubtful. And that Variation and Exemption from Rule may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed rather from their Particular Diſpenſation, than the choice or Liberty of him that is Singular.</p>
            <p>Now what thoſe Caſes are, which may require an Equitable, or Favourable ſenſe, rather than Literal, or Rigorous, ſome may preſume to aſſign, and I for my Part could alledge, not only the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitableneſs, in great Part, not abſolute (for I make no doubt but conſiderable Benefit doth redound to the Deaf, and not actually hearing, being preſent dutifully at the Miniſtration of Gods Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer in Publick Prayers) of ſuch as are at Church at the time of the Communion Service at the Altar: But mine own Infirmity, which you know, hath of late Years appeared too Notorious: But I hold it more prudent to refer things of this nature to be judged and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in a Synod, which God in his due time ſend for the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of ſuch Errours, Obliquities, and Defects, as have and muſt neceſſarily creep into a Church without more Frequent, General, and Publick Review of the Rules of Diſcipline, than hath of late Years been allowed. And ſo I conclude, profeſſing all readineſs to ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions above mine own Underſtanding, not exceeding my Bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Power alſo.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:56533:11"/>
               <head>Preliminary Reflections to the Enſuing Treatiſe, occaſioned by two Papers of the ſame Subject.</head>
               <p>IN the beginning of <hi>March</hi> laſt receiving from a very good Friend and Reverend Brother (I may more truely ſay Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) a Printed Treatiſe entitled <hi>Pariſh Churches turned into Conventicles,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein the Author endeavoured to ſhew that the Miniſtration of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> not performed at the Communion-Table (which he ſuppoſed to be commanded by the Church) rendred the whole, <hi>Conventicling;</hi> and being deſired to give mine Opinion of the ſame, I, tho under great Indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at that time, applyed my ſelf to declare my Judgement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in manner following: which I returned to them that ſame Week, not intending to have it made Publick.</p>
               <p>But in <hi>July</hi> following receiving from the ſame hands two Papers more, the one called <hi>Pariſh Churches no Conventicles, &amp;c.</hi> in a Letter to his Friend <hi>N. D.</hi> and the other, whoſe Title was, <hi>Moderation a Vertue: Or a Vindication of the Principles and Practiſes of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Divines and Laity of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in which an Appendix was ſpecially added againſt the foreſaid Treatiſe of <hi>Churches turn'd into Conventicles,</hi> (of which alſo I was deſired to give my Senſe) I perceiving both the Replyers commended Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration ſo much, thought they, nor any of their Perſwaſion, could take it much amiſs, if I ſtepped in between the two Extremes. <hi>viz.</hi> the Gentleman, and his two Adverſaries.</p>
               <p>And to this Purpoſe I muſt declare my ſelf to be much Scandaliz'd with the Title of the Gentleman's Book: but upon later Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that himſelf upon better thoughts, was not very well pleaſed with it, I reſted better ſatisfied, and ſo ſhould others too, if it be ſo. How far I approved the Work my following Diſcourſe will ſhew. On
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56533:12"/> the other ſide, when I diſcovered ſo much Gall, and Bitterneſs on his Adverſaries Part, eſpecially by <hi>O. V.</hi> I could not well brook the Treatment they gave him, even ſuppoſing he erred, and they had hit the Mark.</p>
               <p>But eſpecially, I obſerved how both were weakly hurried down the Torrent of Vulgar Acceptation and Senſe of Moderation: which doubtleſs they ought better a great deal to have underſtood, before they built upon ſuch a Slippery, Sandy Foundation the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of their Tottering Diſcourſes. For to me this ſeems to be the great occaſion of Diviſions, and Schiſms, that every man fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to himſelf a Mean, and Moderation; comparing himſelf with himſelf: And becauſe he can inſtance in ſome on both hands, that differ from him, and therefore muſt needs be extream, he applauds himſelf, as having hit the Golden Mean: Defining Moderation, as he in <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> did Man.</p>
               <p>For being demanded what was Man, anſwered wiſely, <hi>Socrates</hi> is a Man, and himſelf was a Man. So theſe men being demanded, what is true Moderation, in effect anſwer, It is to do as they do, and to be able to ſhew that both ſides of them do otherwiſe than they. Whereas upon due Examination, according to the Rule of Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, either of ſuch Extreams (as they call them) are more Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate than what they magnifie for ſuch. And to ſuch Moderation as this, Preduce Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Unlearned, as well, as Vain and Vile Diſtinction of Occaſional Communion: As if conſtant Communion were not Occaſional alſo: And his Occaſional Communion with the Church of <hi>England</hi> (a little to turn the edge of the Arguments proving him to be ſuch) were not conſtant Schiſmaticalneſs, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this Plauſible Shuffle.</p>
               <p>If Occaſional Communion be the thing they approve, why do they not Communicate with the Church, but when they have no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to go to a Conventicle, and perhaps play the Miniſter there? By which, Occaſional going to Maſs, and more conſtantly to a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, may be called Moderation too. And if ſome men of the Church of <hi>England</hi> leave the Communion-Service quite out, while others uſe it in the Desk, they may be termed men of Moderation too: As he that lays claim to an whole Eſtate, tho moſt unjuſtly, is a moderate Man, if he acquieſces with one Field or two for Peace ſake, when not a Foot is by Law due unto him.</p>
               <p>And doth not the preſent Moderation come to this, as if the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Church ſhould ſay thus, as they truly may. We have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56533:12"/> by innumerable falſe, and wicked Slanders caſt upon the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Governours, and Service of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected many People from them all: And having ſo done, we ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably and ſucceſsfully took Arms, and beat them all down, and confounded them; but an overruling Power and Providence cauſing us to let go our hold, and vomit up that ſweet Morſel we had once ſwallowed, we now addreſs our ſelves to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that they would Fairly, and Peaceably, and Charitably give all again for the asking for: and if not all at once, by Degrees: Firſt granting one thing, then another, and then a third, and ſo on; our Arguments and Reaſons being always as valid for what remains, as for what ſhall be yielded to us, and we continuing as unquiet and reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs until we be poſſeſſed of all, as we were before any thing was granted to us; and this Motive being always obliging Peace, and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which we promiſe to keep with them of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> when they ſhall in this manner become of our Religion. O Singular Charity, and Divine Moderation!</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs our Author of <hi>Moderation a Vertue,</hi> makes an offer <hi>Pag.</hi> 23, 24. as if he would unriddle this Abſtruſe Notion; and tell us what is Moderation: But finding (as it ſhould ſeem) the task too hard and dangerous, and ſo hot, that it would burn his Fingers, and cauſe him to let go his Pen Writing for it; after a flouriſhing promiſe, he falls quite off from the true Queſtion, and Difficulty, and leaves it to ſhift, and plead for it ſelf: and betakes himſelf to the Commendation of the great vertue or habit of a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate or Moderate Mind, and Diſpoſition: Which is very fine, and laudable, but nothing at all to his purpoſe; which was to declare unto us <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Mediocrity of the thing, as the Philoſopher ſpeaks. He ſhould have told us which was the true Mean in Religion, which was the Moderate Worſhip of God between two vicious Extreams: but this he either conſidered not, or more wiſely than faithfully avoided. For I doubt not, (whatever he doth) but a Papiſt, a Quaker, a Presbyterian, a Jew, a Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan may be a very Moderate and well Temper'd Man of mind, and Modeſt: but what is this to our choice of our Religion from the Equity of the ſame, and Moderateneſs?</p>
               <p>And yet this Moderator himſelf was but little acquainted with this Vertue he commends, as may appear by his taking into ſuch rude, and ridiculous Conſideration, a Sermon laying forth the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of Pretenders to ſuch Moderation as he fancies: But that I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56533:13"/> meddle not with, as quite from my purpoſe: Yet is it not ſo Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, as his extremities in wringing the Noſe of all Canons and Rubricks of the Church, which he ſtomachs, with ſo much and ſtrange violence of interpretation, that he forces blood from them. According to which Practice we ſhall never be able to underſtand one another any longer than we talk together, nor then neither, our Backs being a little turned, and ſuch canvaſſing uſed.</p>
               <p>But we ſuppoſing that the Conſtitutions and Canons of the Church, tho, (as in ſuch Caſes it muſt neceſſarily happen) ſome few may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of various Conſtructions, were much more clear and intelligible before, and without his Scholy, than with it; we earneſtly demand of theſe Reformers of Reformation, and Moderators of Mederation, before they ſo apertly preſume to modellize the Church according to their Scantling, to give us the true Notion of Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in more General Terms than hitherto; that we may know bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter how to accommodate our ſelves to their Expectations: And Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that they would ſet about the work to purpoſe, and prove by good Rules and Authority (not their own, the worſt and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all men) that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as now conſtituted in all it's Habiliments, Rites, and Ceremonies, is not the moſt Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Church can be produced, or inſtanced in by them.</p>
               <p>Nay, I will venture to add one Challenge more, If we cannot make it appear upon better Ground, that more might be added, than any of them ſhall bring, that more ſhould be taken away than is, then we will loſe our Cauſe, and they ſhall Triumph with Cauſe, who have hitherto without Cauſe.</p>
               <p>This we would not have ſaid, but that we are perſwaded we can do it, and that upon this, our unquiet, and querulous Brethren would ceaſe their Complaints, and reſt ſatisfied with the preſent State of things, leſt a worſe thing happen unto them. For tho I approve not that ſaying which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> notes as moſt dangerous to them, and Notorious, nor can I tell, but by his Reports, ever any ſuch thing was ſaid of Diſſenters: That if they would not be quiet, they ſhould have more things to trouble them: Yet I ſay this, according to all indifferent Rules of Judgment, it is altogether as reaſonable that the Ceremonies of the Church ſhould be more Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, as they can make it, that thoſe we have, ſhould be aboliſhed, or fewer.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, we demand of theſe men, if they cannot give us the true, and genuine Definition of Moderation, they would at leaſt draw up
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56533:13"/> ſuch a Scheme of Religion, as ſhall be accounted by their own Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, moderate, and not extream. I confeſs I have met with a late Pamphlet, which ſeems to aim at ſuch an end, bearing this Title, <hi>The Woe of Scandal,</hi> ſhewing the evil of impoſing things on mens Conſciences <hi>Acknowledged to be indifferent.</hi> This Title im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports a cloſer State of Matters than others, but how he manages his Cauſe, I cannot ſay, having not read two Leaves, if Pages in it: And in truth, I ſaw no Reaſon why I ſhould, had I but little elſe to do; conſidering how his clearer State of matters is a perverting the whole Controverſie. This being the truer State of our Differences, <hi>viz.</hi> The Woe of Scandal belonging to all ſuch as refuſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to all ſuch things as are acknowledged to be indifferent; Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority, and Judges of ſuch matters requiring them.</p>
               <p>But leaving that, I return to <hi>Moderation a Vertue,</hi> who in his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix againſt Mr. <hi>Hart,</hi> or <hi>T. A.</hi> as he calls him, would fortifie his looſe Senſe of Moderation, <hi>Page</hi> 78, 79. by a number of eminent, and Learned Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſome of them, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers profeſſed Enemies thereof, until Lucre, and Ambition open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Eyes to diſſemble their Nonconformity, and who theſe are, I leave the Reader to judge, as is very eaſie; and therefore unfit to ſway in this matter. Others I acknowledge were truly of the Church, and yet commended highly Moderation: But what kind of Moderation? The Vertue, not the new Model. And that is not at all to his purpoſe, but againſt the bitter Spirits, and ſtrange groundleſs Animoſities of Diſſenters, who had they their Wills, would tear Kings from their Thrones (as very lately they have endeavoured) and Biſhops from their Sees, for to put down Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and think their own Blood, and the Blood of others well ſhed to accompliſh theſe ends, as Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> for one, hath ſaid.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I grant that ſome Learned, and Good men of our Church were much diſpoſed to a Remiſſion of ſome things Eſtabliſhed; But I pray upon what Grounds? Any taken from the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves appointed? very rarely do we meet with any ſuch: Or from the Perſons or Parties aggrieved with them? This was moſt uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. But firſt, they ſhould have conſidered, that the Relaxation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded was as grievous to others, as the impoſition to them. Next, this was only during the fair Face, and carriage of many good Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd, and in General, well affected to Religion, but cheated into a Prejudice againſt the Forms of the Church by Pious frauds: But when the Impoſthume broke out into ſuch a foul Ulcer, as made
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56533:14"/> them, and their cloſe deſign ſtink in the Noſtrils of all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and honeſt men, not too far drawn into their Net, they chang'd their Minds, and bent their Doctrine, and Diſcourſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the Immoderate Paſſions of the Mind, than the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate Worſhip, as ours was, and is ſtill ſlanderouſly called.</p>
               <p>This I ſpeak not without as great, and good Authority, as any ingenious man can deſire, and that is of Sr. <hi>Francis Walſingham</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary to Queen <hi>Elazabeth,</hi> and one that was once (till Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence better taught him) a real, tho moderate Favourer of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Party in thoſe days: And thus writes he of them, in his Letter to Mounſieur <hi>Critoy,</hi> which you have in the Cloſe of the 2<hi>d.</hi> part of Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Hiſtory of the Reformation, in theſe words, <hi>Pag.</hi> 420. <q>For the other Party, which have been Offenſive to the State, tho in another Degree, which named themſelves Reformers, and We commonly called Puritans, this hath been the Proceedings towards them. A great while, when they inveighed againſt ſuch abuſes in the Church, as <hi>Pluralities, Non-reſidence,</hi> and the like, their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Zeal was not condemned, only their Violence was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times cenſured. When they refuſed the uſe of ſome Ceremonies, and Rites as Superſtitious, they were tolerated with much Conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence, and Gentleneſs.</q> 
                  <q>Yea, when they called in Queſtion the Superiority of Biſhops, and pretended to a Democracy in the Church, yet their Propoſitions were conſidered, and contrary Writings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated and diſcuſſed. Yet all this while it was perceived that their Courſe was dangerous and very Popular. As becauſe Papiſtry was odions, therefore it was ever in their Mouths that they ought to purge the Church from the Reliques of Papiſtry: A thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the People, who love ever to run from one Extream to another.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here you may firſt obſerve that the Church of <hi>England</hi> in it's Reformation ſtands between two Extreams, and I think that is to be Moderate. And next you may ſee by late effects, what is the end of the many Specious and Pious Pretences of theſe Moderators; and gather what it is ever like to be: Who are wont (not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) not to cut the main Timbers of our Conſtitutions apieces at a blow, but Chip by Chip: Which they call Mercifulneſs, and Moderation, as that, which may be ſpared till all be ſpoiled. And I could inſtance in ſome of theſe his Witneſſes of Moderation, who have taken their Leſſon out of <hi>Socinus,</hi> and cant with the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians</hi> about Liberty, and forbearance, themſelves being in no Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56533:14"/> to domineer, as the <hi>Arminians</hi> did once being uppermoſt: But now (good Men!) brought under Original Sin, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Doctrine of it, is but an unneceſſary Doctrine, or rather falſe Doctrine, but Liberty of Prophecying, true. And the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Trinity muſt not oblige, but as a thing, which may, or may not be received. And <hi>Holy Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Holy Jeſus</hi> over and over again, muſt ſtand inſtead of ſuch uſual Appellations whereby he ſhould be known to be God and Man.</p>
               <p>And all this I take to proceed from the Moderate, but Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical <hi>Dogme</hi> found in the Caſes of Conſcience of that Great Man, <hi>viz.</hi> That nothing muſt be impoſed, but what the Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: And this Grounded on the Reaſon of <hi>Calvin,</hi> and his late Admirers, leſt otherwiſe our Governours ſhould multiply Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions without meaſure: Upon which Ground we may Null the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of our Natural and Civil Parents, who certainly may exceed due Bounds in their Commands, and therefore the ſafeſt way would be to deprive them of all: And thus under Colour of Liberty, and Moderate Government ſhall we ſee <hi>Anarchy</hi> both in Church and State, untill the Intolerableneſs of that conſtrain to accept of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, perhaps much more Tyrannical, tho managed by many Men; being aſhamed to return to that which they caſt off for leſs Cauſes than they have, to quit themſelves of that they have Imprudently brought upon themſelves.</p>
               <p>But no more of that Subject, ſomething being due to this Authors Act, and Project of diſtorting, miſconſtruing, confounding, and in effect Nulling all Canons and Rubricks lying in his way for ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences ſake; that ſo the Rules, and Practices of the Church being made aequilibrious, and indifferent, or perhaps of no Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at all, Liberty for ſuch Conſciences may be allowed, and the feat ſucceed more ſoftly, but no leſs ſurely than by open Defiances, and Ruptures.</p>
               <p>But ought he not here alſo to have told us what is a Tender Conſcience, and who they are that claim Benefit from ſuch Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? For how little good that Plea can do any Fanatically diſpoſed, will appear from theſe Reaſons. Firſt, that we of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> pretend as ſtrongly, and more reaſonably, to Tenderneſs of Conſcience upon parting with ſuch Rites and Ceremonies, as they can do in oppoſing or avoiding them: Shall we therefore take a Thorn out of their Toe, and put it in our own? If they ſay we acknowledge them to be indifferent, and ſo, ſuch as may be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56533:15"/> omitted for Peace ſake, we ſay they likewiſe muſt, and do hold the ſame indifferency in Nature, as we do, and therefore ought no leſs to accept of them for Peace and Unity ſake. Yea, more obliged are they to this, than we, to the other, Authority lawful turning the Scales on our ſide.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we directly deny that the Party can be ſaid to be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſcienced, when as ſuch monſtrous Acts and Effects of them, not as ſingle Private men, but as Proſecutors and Advancers of their Faction, all along from the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign to this preſent day, and moſt of all, and lateſt of all, have appeared to prove the contrary. And the Sins that are theirs, as United, are they we are to judge them by, and not thoſe of Perſons only. So that Thirdly if they have tender Conſciences, we cannot poſſible know that they have ſuch, tho they tell us never ſo often, and loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they are the Men above others, that are ſo qualified. And therefore this not appearing, is as not being, to us: And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, can be no Rule, or motive to induce us upon ſuch blind Grounds, to leave our Station.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, if they had tender Conſciences, and we knew it, it could be no good, nor wiſe Act in us who (as is ſaid) have as great, and juſt a claim to that Pretence as they, for us to relieve them to our own miſchief.</p>
               <p>And thus have I done with the Moderator Writing againſt them, who are no Friends to his Grindallizers, and Trimmers, as it ſeems the words are now adays, which I knew not before I learnt ſo much from his Title Page: And might have well doubted, whether this lover of Moderation; that is, he knows not what, be Reſident upon his Cure, as he there alſo profeſſes to avoid the Suſpition of the Leader of a Conventicle: But in truth he doth not attain this end, there being ſo many ways of Equivocation invented now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies to ſeem what men are not, and not to ſeem what they are, that 'tis not incredible that his Cure may be a gathered Church, tho I knowing nothing of that, affirm no more than I know.</p>
               <p>But now I apply my ſelf more particularly to <hi>O. V.</hi> and his Letter to his Friend <hi>N. D.</hi> both true Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as they Write themſelves: But I think they ſhould have added to that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, this Supplement, <hi>For ought they know.</hi> For there is great Suſpicion that <hi>O. V.</hi> hath taken ſome of his Inſtructions from the Conference of <hi>Worceſter-Houſe,</hi> as Printed and Publiſhed by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, where this Sentence of <hi>Socrates</hi> in his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56533:15"/> 
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. 23. is made great uſe of to the ſame end, that is, as little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as here, <hi>viz. Thoſe of the ſame Faith differ as to Cuſtom from one another.</hi> Can this reach Mr. <hi>Hart</hi>'s Caſe, think we? Or ſo much as prove any ſuch Moderation of Rites, and Ceremonies our Church requires.</p>
               <p>This the Conferrers, and ſurely this our Preſent Vindicator ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, deceived by them in all Probability: But they are all much miſtaken. For <hi>Socrates</hi> meant nothing leſs than to countenance, or ſo much as to ſay, that any Church in the Chriſtian World, in thoſe, or Ancienter Days did ever allow any of their Subordinate Members to differ from the Rules of their Reſpective Churches, or to differ from them in Rites and Ceremonies, and leaſt of all in ſuch things which were preſcribed them in the Service of God. But this is the plain and certain Caſe between the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Diſſenters, and their Advocates pleading for Moderation and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in things ſtanding determined by their Superiours. But <hi>Socrates</hi> tells us how ſeveral Churches of ſeveral Nations, and Provinces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Coordinate Governours, did uſe their known Liberty in forming the external part of Gods Publick Worſhip, ſomewhat diverſly. And doth the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or any of it's Defenders ſpeak, write, or act otherwiſe? This were indeed blame-worthy, but no ſuch thing appears, and therefore Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> of <hi>Eaton</hi> famous for his Learning, might have ſhewn his Judgement, as well as his Reading, if he had made no ſuch uſe of ſuch Inſtances as theſe, and taught others ſo to do.</p>
               <p>To this ſtumble in the very Threſhold, I might add another Errour charged upon Mr. <hi>Hart</hi> in the Title Page, which pretends Mr. <hi>Hart</hi> defames the Church of <hi>England</hi> contrary to the <hi>11th.</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of thoſe 1603. But I find no ſuch Defamation chargeable upon Mr. <hi>Hart,</hi> nor proved by him, as is attempted <hi>Page</hi> 3. The Canon, even as quoted by him, ſpeaks thus, <hi>To affirm and maintain, that there are within this Realm, other Meetings, Aſſemblies, or Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Kings born Subjects, than ſuch as by the Laws of this Land, are held, and allowed, which may rightly challenge to themſelves the Name of true and Lawful Churches.</hi> This is all with him, but ſcarce ſenſe without that which follows in the Canon, <hi>Let him be Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now the matter is, how to bring to this, any thing that Mr. <hi>Hart</hi> ſays in any place of his Book: The moſt, and worſt that he hath in all his Book is the Title, <hi>Pariſh Churches turned into Conventicles,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:56533:16"/> &amp;c. Does this at all contradict the Canon mentioned, which flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denies all Aſſemblies in oppoſition to our Church to be any true Churches? The Canon does not ſo much as ſay that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is the true Church, therefore he that ſhould ſay it is no true Church, doth not defame it upon the account of that Canon, tho upon others he doth. But I cannot think it was ever in Mr. <hi>Hart</hi>'s mind to deny the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be a true Church, but to affirm that ſuch Pariſh Churches as did deviate from ſuch Preſcriptions as he conceived all were obliged to, in that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, did Symbolize with Conventicles; in which acceptation, his meaning is more juſt, and ſincere, than to be confuted either by your, or my Labours.</p>
               <p>And this probably you found by Experience, and therefore you more wiſely, than juſtly relinquiſh the true State of the Caſe, and all along fall upon his Perſon, and Qualifications with greateſt Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilities, and Reproaches, becoming rather the Son of a Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, than a Son of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> which manner of Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation I have choſen chiefly to except againſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you acknowledge him to be a Gentleman; you had in my opinion, done much more adviſedly, and peradventure more ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully, if you had ſhewn your ſelf to have been ſuch too, by Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Uſage, and eſpecially if you be of the Clergy (which I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know, nor have enquired after,) to your Civility you ſhould have added a Degree of Modeſty more. It may be remembred how above Forty Years ago, a Biſhop's unadviſedly caſting out a word, which was drawn to imply a Contempt of Gentlemen, it gave ſuch Alarm to many Gentlemen, and ſo Incenſed them againſt that Order, if not the Clergy in General, that it contributed not a little to their Sufferings. It had been Prudence therefore to have been more ſparing of your Spittle in that reſpect.</p>
               <p>And ſo Secondly, as a Bariſter, and Lawyer; a Friend and Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willer to the Church, would have omitted the many Taunts, and Revilings you have caſt upon him as ſuch. Do you not conſider how much it becomes the Clergy to mitigate the Prejudices that Order are too Subject to againſt the Church, and how powerful they are, to ſtrengthen or weaken the Intereſt of the Church, and it's Proſperity? Another man, not inferiour to you, would have found occaſion of Gratitude, and Praiſe, from whence you raiſe your reproaches, <hi>viz.</hi> that with honeſt, and ſincere mind, and good Ingenuity, he zealouſly undertook the Aſſerting of the Rights, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56533:16"/> Rites of the Church: Wherein if he failed, as I my ſelf am of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion he did, tho I cannot ſay, that either I, or you have Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo much, it was a laudable intention tending to it's Vindication from private Interpreters of it's Laws, and Corrupters too, as he judged. His ſeverity in drawing ſuch Concluſions from ſuch a ſuppoſed Senſe, gave me occaſion to imagine he might be a Lawyer, whoſe property it is to condemn a whole Deed for a Raſure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in it: he conceiving that this omiſſion of the due Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the ſecond Service was of that nature.</p>
               <p>But do you think it requiſite, or tolerable, that every ordinary Miniſter ſhould ſo modifie his Worſhip (as the Presbyterians in their Books ſpeak) or ſo uſe their Diſcretion as in truth rather to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Diſcretion of the Multitude and Common People, than their own, or the Churches? There is not any thing more unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a wiſe or humble Miniſter than this, knowing that to be true, which <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, <hi>de Vita Beata Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Vulgus veritatis peſſimus In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpres,</hi> The Common ſort are the worſt Interpreters of truth, of all Men; yea, taking in what there preſently followeth, <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus autem tam Chlamydatum, quam Coronam voco,</hi> I mean, ſaith he, by the Vulgar, ſome Robed, or Gowned Perſons, as well as the Rabble, and ſo we Miniſters may be in danger to be of the Number, and ſo we are indeed compared with our Governours.</p>
               <p>Once more, <hi>Seneca</hi> in the ſame Place againſt Courters of the Common People, <hi>Argumentum Peſſimi Turba eſt,</hi> 'Tis an Argument the thing is very bad, which the Rout approves very much. Did you never hear of the Expert Maſter of Muſick, who gave his Scholar a Box of the Ear when he took him playing to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of the Vulgar, Preſuming he muſt needs be out, and play amiſs, or the Common Sort would never have liked him ſo well? Which it were to be wiſhed were not too often to be found in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Preachers, who the worſe they Preach, the more they are applauded by ſuch People whom <hi>Chaucer</hi> in his Squires Tale thus deſcribes but too truely.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>As People deemeth commonly</l>
                  <l>Of things that been more Subtilly</l>
                  <l>Then they can in their leudneſs Comprehend,</l>
                  <l>They deemen gladly to the badder end.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And ſuch are the Judges we commonly chooſe to be directed by.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:56533:17"/>
               <p> But I paſs that, and come to a worſe reproach than the former by far, an Argument of a very mean Underſtanding and low Spirit in the Accuſer, <hi>viz. That he was once a Papiſt, and tho Converted, ſtill looking towards</hi> Rome; an Imprudent, and Unchriſtian Aſperſion. 'Tis true, as I am informed, in his greener and younger Days, he fell into the Snares of <hi>Rome:</hi> And 'tis no leſs true, and more to the honour of our Religion, that in his Maturer Judgment and Years returning to himſelf, he returned to the Church of <hi>England</hi> alſo, and preferring it above all other Faiths, or Factions, deſires no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than an exact Obſervation of her Rules and Manner of divine Worſhip.</p>
               <p>And this Laſt it ſeems, ſo troubles you, as it does a great many more ſuch true Proteſtants which the ſelate times have produced, or rather brought to light to the diſgrace of all Reformation, that you take Liberty to mock and rail him out of that Conſcientious deſign, ſuſpecting the Invalidity of your Argumentations to that end. For as we ſee it to be the crafty Practice of Pilferers, and Thieves having ſtole any thing from their Neighbours, the firſt thing they do is to pull off, or deface the Mark, that it may not be known to whom it belongs: ſo Phanatically diſpoſed Perſons make it their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs to tear away the Rites and Ceremonies belonging to, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racterizing the Worſhip of the Church of <hi>England</hi> from the Will-Worſhip of Sectaries, that it may become their own without Controul.</p>
               <p>But are ſuch reproaches as you give to one converted to our Religion the beſt Entertainment, and welcome you can afford out of the Penury of your Civility, or true Piety? Have you a mind to drive him back again, and turn him out of Doors by your ill uſage? Or is this the Encouragement you can give to others to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to us? I will here tell you a true ſtory to this purpoſe, which ſome Seamen, with whom ſome Years ſince I was embarked, told me upon their own knowledge, which may ſuffice to advertize you of your abſurdity in reviling Converts for having been in Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. A <hi>Moor,</hi> or <hi>Turk</hi> was of the Ships Company who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced Mahometaniſme, and became a Chriſtian. An ill nurtur'd and malicious Fellow among them bearing him a ſpite, would of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten be reviling him for his Religion, calling him <hi>Mahometan,</hi> and worſe. To whom the Man anſwered Ingenuouſly and Soberly, What means this Man to check and reproach me ſo, for having been a Mahometan? I was ſo indeed, but now I am as good a Chriſtian as himſelf. It happened about the ſame time, that theſe things thus
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56533:17"/> paſſed, that there was an occaſion for the Engliſh Railer to go up to the main top, whence he was ſuddenly hurried away by a Blaſt of Wind (as was ſuppoſed) being never ſeen, or heard of more: Which they told me, as an Inſtance of Gods Judgment upon a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viler of a Penitent, and I tell you.</p>
               <p>But you ſay, He looks towards <hi>Rome</hi> again. How know you that? Have you turned his Face that way in Abhorrence of your baſe Treatment? I might ſo judge, but that I am perſwaded nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Evil, nor your good Word is of any account with him, you ſhould ſeem rather to be one of the Moderneſt true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants or as the late expreſſion of a dying Man is, <hi>Sincere Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant,</hi> who make all Popiſhly affected, not approving their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanations of Gods Service, and Seditious Zeal.</p>
               <p>But I ſuppoſe you ground your Suſpitions from what you here charge him with, <hi>Irreverence at the Miniſters Prayer, and Sermon, which in one of our Statutes</hi> (ſay you) <hi>whether he knows it or no, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Divine Service, by Reading ſome Book of his own,</hi> &amp;c. And I alſo am one of thoſe, that know not any Statute, or Canon where the Sermon is called Divine Service: And whatever may be ſaid in large acceptation of Words, I am ſure it is not ſo in it's nature, and proper uſe of Divine Worſhip. And I am ſure alſo, the Prayer of the Miniſter in his Pulpit before Sermon is no part of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice enjoyned, but a Will-worſhip of Mens Private Invention, more like to that of <hi>Nadab,</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> than that of the eſtabliſhed Worſhip which Sectaries have been wont ſo to traduce. And if the Gentleman ſo carried himſelf at Church at ſuch Private Exerciſes, he offends leſs againſt the Conſtitutions of the Church, than they, who ſhew their Gifts rather than their Grace in uſing them; whoſe Original and Deſign was to bring the Worſhip of God appointed by the Church, into diſgrace, and contempt, which accordingly Succeeded in late Years.</p>
               <p>And if you plead a Cuſtom, (as my ſelf do againſt the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of miniſtring conſtantly at the Communion-Table) I may anſwer, Firſt, this Cuſtom hath not the like Grounds, or Reaſon, which it ſeemeth to me the forbearance of that hath. Again, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom may make it Tolerable to do ſo, but not Intolerable, or Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56533:18"/> to let it alone: So that if any tender Conſcience ſhall be offended at ſuch ſtrange Fire offer'd to God, ſuch a one may, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Cuſtom, modeſtly declare it's diſlike by doing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe, not Scandalous in it ſelf. And therefore, tho the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be beholden to him that ſhall joyn with him in that Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (if as Mr. <hi>Cawdry</hi> and others of his Strain ſuppoſe, <hi>Superſtitio</hi> be <hi>Supra Statutum)</hi> and incommanded Worſhip, yet no man can Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally cenſure him that refuſes to hear ſuch Exorbitances.</p>
               <p>And the ſame may be ſaid of the Pſalms Sung in Meeter and Tunes of Private Inventions. I confeſs I have Read lately in the Writings of two Reverend, and Learned Divines, that it is a Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Errour to ſay that thoſe Singing Pſalms want Lawful Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: But very deſirous to know where and what that Authority is, I found my ſelf Fruſtrated, and am ſo ſmall an Antiquary in ſuch abſtruſe things, that I cannot help my ſelf herein: But have been ſometimes of opinion, that if any ſuch Authority there be, as thoſe Reverend Perſons intimate, but inſtance not in, that it muſt rather belong to another Ancienter, and (in my Judgment) more Pious and Elaborate (as to Art, and Senſe, tho no leſs uncouth in Language) Tranſlation in Verſe which I have by me, and ſeems to be the Work either of one Man, or divers concurring to the ſame thing, and not Patch'd up by ſeveral Authors, as the Common Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pſalms are; poſſibly that Ancienter I ſpeak of, may be the ſame, which the Author of the Troubles of <hi>Eranckford</hi> Speaks of, who tells us, <hi>After the Death of Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>the Exiled prepare themſelves to depart for</hi> England <hi>from</hi> Geneva, <hi>ſave ſuch as ſtayed to finiſh the Tranſlation of the Bible, and Pſalms, both in Meeter and Proſe.</hi> Which yet whether they were ever allowed by Authority, Iſtill remain Ignorant.</p>
               <p>And thus I have paſſed ſome General Animadverſions on the Cenſurers of Mr. <hi>Hart</hi>'s Book: Not intending to call in Queſtion their particular Examinations, from which I might have drawn ſomewhat pertinent to mine own Method of the ſame Subject: But I chooſe rather to let it paſs rudely according to the firſt and only Draught by me: Whereby I ſuppoſe that if Mediocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Moderation be ſuch a Vertue as it is cryed up for, I may in this particular claim that Praiſe, and obſtain the Approbation
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56533:18"/> of theſe Commenders of it, Submitting what I ſay, not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to them, but moſt of all to ſuch as are over me in the Lord, from whoſe Determination I ſhall hardly ſwerve.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
